(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Markle.
- My name is Catherine and
today we've got a monologue.
We've got one person talking, telling
you how to make the perfect sandwich.
- That's right, she's a chef
and she's gonna teach us.
She's gonna talk about all the ingredients
and some tips on how to make a sandwich.
So be prepared.
This is gonna be a really good lesson.
- And I'm already hungry thinking about it.
So let's listen to the dialogue.
We'll be back in a moment.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome to our show.
Today I'm going to show you how to
make the perfect mouthwatering sandwich.
Are you ready?
Let's get started.
Let's start with the basics, bread.
Bread is an important ingredient here.
You need to remember one thing.
Choose the bread according
to the following criteria.
Freshness, crumb, and color.
If you want a closed sandwich,
I recommend you first toast
your bread in a toaster or oven
or grill it slightly until it
gets a light brown color.
Now that our bread is ready,
let's talk about the ingredients.
Of course, each person's palette is different,
but I'm going to give you a few tips
that you'll be able to use when turning
any sandwich into the perfect sandwich.
I would strongly recommend you
put fresh vegetables in your sandwich.
Do not undervalue them
as they play a big role
in forming the taste and we'll make
the sandwich more refreshing and light.
The best traces here are evident.
Cucumbers, tomatoes,
onions, sweet pepper or chili,
lettuce, and of course herbs,
you can't go wrong with them.
As for arborgines,
mushrooms, and asparagus,
I would recommend you first grill them
slightly with a little touch of olive oil.
Last but not least, we
have a wide variety of
condiments that we can
add to our perfect sandwich.
We can be subtle and add
just a touch of salt and pepper
or we can combine mustard
sauce, mayonnaise, ketchup,
or even caviar to
achieve a stronger flavor.
It's always a good idea to cut
your sandwich in triangles or
manageable pieces to avoid
all your ingredients falling out
and standing your shirt.
That's all the time we have for today,
but join us next time where we'll be
going over how to make the perfect lasagna.
So, next time.
(upbeat music)
All right, we're back.
So obviously, I think she
knows what she's talking about.
This is gonna be a great sandwich.
All right, so as she mentioned,
a lot of ingredients, a
couple of different words
that we might not understand.
So let's take a look at them
now in language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
Okay, at the beginning of this monologue,
as I said, the chef is talking about things
that you need to look for in a bread
because bread is the base of a sandwich.
And she mentioned the word crumb.
Okay, yeah, she said
freshness, crumb, and color.
So what does she mean
by crumb of the bread?
Okay, so crumb, a crumb, is a very, very,
very, very, very small piece of bread.
Like when you put bread in a toaster,
maybe it's what falls down, actually.
We call them bread crumbs sometimes.
You can cook with
them, but they're basically
little pieces of bread
that fall off, little grains.
Okay, yeah, so yeah, usually
it happens all the time.
You're having cookies, or
you're having some bread.
You bite into it, and
little pieces of bread
or cookie fall down,
those are called crumbs.
That's right, and this is a
very, and I wanna remind
everyone that the word crumb
has a B on the end, C-R-U-M-B.
But we don't pronounce
the B, we just say crumb.
- Yeah, you don't say crumb, no.
- Okay, so just crumb.
- Yeah, be careful with that one.
- All right, so we have to keep it look out
for the crumb of the bread,
I guess, how fresh and how,
sometimes when you squeeze
bread, it makes it a nice little sound.
- Crunch. - Crunch.
- Exactly, so, but she's also recommending
a couple of different
ingredients, and she
said, well, it depends
on each person's palate.
So after we've chosen our bread,
she talks about a closed
sandwich and maybe toasting it.
- Okay, so there are two
options for sandwiches.
You might see these on menus, as
well as when you're cooking yourself.
A closed sandwich means
you have two pieces of bread,
one on the bottom, and
one on top, it's closed.
- Okay.
- But the opposite is an open sandwich.
That means you only
have one piece of bread,
and then maybe you
have some meat on top.
- Oh, okay.
Actually, I always
thought that for it to be a
sandwich, you had to
have two pieces of bread.
- Well, now when you, I would challenge you
to look on Google for open-faced sandwich,
or open sandwich, you'll find
some very interesting things.
- Yeah, I've had them.
Actually, you can put
some meat in some cheese,
just on top of a piece of
bread, and you're done.
- I'm a huge fan of those, yeah.
- So that's a closed sandwich,
though, when you have two
pieces of bread, and the meat
in the middle, and after that,
she talks a little bit
about people's tastes
and what people want, but
she used a very special word.
- That's right.
She said, each person's
palate is different.
Okay, a palate in the
context of food and taste
means the way that food
flavors affect a person individually.
- That's right.
So sometimes you say that some
people have very good palate,
so they can maybe tell the
difference between a wine
from 1978, and a wine from
1980, or something like that.
- That's right.
So you can have a
palate, a good palate for
wine, but also in this
case, what I'm about food,
I could say, I have a
very sensitive palate,
so I don't like to use
very, very strong flavors.
- Okay.
So the palate is basically your taste.
It's actually a physical
part of your mouth.
It's the top of your mouth, where your
tongue can touch the top of your mouth.
- They've roofed your mouth, exactly.
And it's not just your
ability to taste sweet.
It's sweet and salty and sour
and all these different flavors.
- Okay, so a person's palate.
Now herbs, right?
Now moving on to the main
ingredient, she mentioned
a lot of easy ones, like
tomatoes, onions, lettuce,
but then we got into a
little bit more specific things.
Like for example, this word that's
always mispronounced, herbs.
- Actually, you can say
herbs, it's a very British thing
to do though, American
to Canadian say herbs.
It has an H in the front,
that's why it's confusing.
- Okay, so we can accept
basically if somebody says herbs,
but I guess in American English, it's
more commonly pronounced as a silent H.
- That's why herbs, herbs.
- And what are herbs you might be asking?
Well, herbs can come in
many different shapes and sizes.
They're usually green,
they're usually grown.
They're ways of giving
food different flavors.
And so basil, for example, is an herb.
It's a big green leaf, something
that we use in pesto, for example.
- Okay.
- You can also have rosemary or mint.
- These are all kinds of herbs.
- Okay, some people
even have an herb garden.
That's right, they grow their own herbs.
- Okay, so now moving on to
these weird looking vegetables,
for example, Aborigines.
- Okay, Aborigines are
the same as eggplants.
So you might hear this word sometimes,
it's basically a big purple vegetable.
- Okay, so for those of you
who haven't seen an Aborigine
or an eggplant, yeah,
it's a big purple vegetable.
They kind of looks like a
cucumber, but a little bit fatter.
Very fat, and if you hold
them, they're not very hard.
They're kind of soft.
And a lot of people like to grill these
or to cook with them
in, for example, Chinese,
with there's a lot of
eggplant or Aborigines.
- All right, so we've had those, we have
mushrooms, and what about asparagus?
- Asparagus is actually one of my favorite
foods, but it's very strange looking.
It's kind of green, and it kind
of has this little head, right?
- That's right, it's long, it's green.
It's kind of like a pencil, but at the
very top, it's kind of like a plant almost.
- Yeah, they have a very strong taste,
and many people don't like asparagus.
- That's right, and the
Germans, I think, actually,
Germans and the Dutch have
special asparagus, that's white.
- Oh, really?
- It's called sparkle.
- Oh, wow.
- But if any of you know what that
is, it's basically a white asparagus,
but asparagus is very popular
in a lot of parts of the world.
- Okay, so now we have our
vegetables, we have our bread,
but now we need to add
a little bit of extra flavor
to the sandwich, so this is
where we add some condiments.
- Okay, so condiments are a category.
You can have many different kinds of
condiments, the most common are salt and pepper.
- Okay, so a condiment
is a category of the things
that you would add flavor
to, as you said, salt, pepper,
but here they mentioned, for
example, mayonnaise or ketchup.
- Ooh, and mustard as
well, these are all condiments.
So in different parts of the world,
they had different kinds of condiments.
I've seen, for example,
a lot of vinegar in Asia.
You can also have pepper
flakes, like in Europe.
- Uh-huh, yeah.
The condiments that you add
to your sandwich are varied.
I've seen people put all types
of condiments in their sandwich,
and for example, one that
may be a little bit strange,
or maybe a little bit more
expensive, condiment is caviar.
- Okay, so caviar is not
always considered a condiment.
It can be, but it can also be eaten alone.
It's basically just fish eggs.
- It's their little fish eggs.
- Very small.
- It always usually, in people's mind,
it's kind of like a fancy food,
very luxurious, very expensive.
- Well, it can be very expensive
if you get like, blue, good caviar.
A lot of caviar comes from
the Caucasus and Russia,
and Ukraine, these places,
and it's very salty in flavor.
- That's right.
So that is also considered
a condiment in our case,
because we're using
it for a sandwich, right?
Okay, so a lot of
words, there are a lot of
interesting things that are
going on in our sandwich.
Why don't we move on
now to Fluency Builder,
where we're gonna take
a look at some phrases.
- Fluency Builder.
- All right, so let's go back
to the very beginning of the
dialogue when she said, all
right, let's start with the basics.
Okay, the basics is a
set phrase in this context.
We can say this about
many different things,
but the basics basically
refers to the most
simple ingredients, or
the most simple elements.
In this case, bread, bread, or meat.
But you can also talk about the basics
in other contexts, like, clothes shopping.
Like, you know, when
school started when I was
a kid, my mom always
used to buy me the basics.
So T-shirts and socks.
- Exactly, so I guess the
basics are the absolute
necessary things, right,
that are also very simple.
So for example, if you talk about dancing,
the basics would be
maybe a certain sequence
of steps that important
essential, right?
- That's right, and would caviar
be a part of the basics, for example?
- No, no, no, no, no, that's an extra.
- Okay, so this is what we
refer to when we say the basics.
Now our chef, when she continued
talking about her sandwich,
she said, "I would strongly recommend
"you use fresh vegetables in your sandwich.
" - Okay, so you can say
I would recommend this,
but to strongly recommend is to have a
very, very strong feeling about something.
- That's right, you're saying
to the person, basically, do it.
You must, yeah.
So if maybe your friend is
sick, you can say something like,
"I would strongly recommend
you go to the doctor today.
" - That means you really,
really should go to the doctor.
- I would be upset if you didn't.
It's kind of formal though.
I don't, it seems like
you would maybe use it
with a boss, with your
boss, or maybe with a person
you don't really know that
well, but with your friend,
you would say, "I really think
you should go to the doctor.
" - Yeah, but you can
say it in both contexts,
but yeah, definitely
more of a formal thing.
- Okay, so we strongly
recommend that you, all right,
so now for our lesson
on this phrase, right?
- Last, last, last, last.
All right, now moving
on to our next phrase.
She, when she started talking about the
condom, and she said, "Last but not least,
we have a wide
variety of condiments.
" - Okay, this is a very,
very common phrase.
It's a set phrase.
You will hear these
words together very often.
Last, but not least.
What could this possibly mean?
So obviously, last
means the last step here.
- The last point.
- But why not least?
- Well, it's not least
important, just because
it's last, it doesn't mean
that it's not important.
Okay, so maybe there are
many people who have to give
presentations in school, and I'm
the very, very last person to go.
The teacher will say, "Last
but not least, Catherine.
" - That's right.
- Makes me feel better.
- Exactly.
- Because you're saying, "You're last,"
but it doesn't mean you're not important.
- Exactly.
So when you wanna make
sure that the last point
of your presentation, or
what you're talking about,
is not ignored, or you
just, you wanna make sure
that everyone knows that
it's also very important,
you say, "It's
last but not least.
" - Great.
- All right, and now last but not
least, the end of fluency builder,
we're gonna close off
with this little phrase.
When she was talking about salt and pepper,
she said, "A touch of salt and pepper.
" - Okay, a touch of salt and
pepper is basically a measure.
It's not a lot, it's very little amount of
salt and pepper, so we can say a touch.
So it's not really a specific
quantity though, right?
We're not saying like a
spoon of salt and pepper.
- Not at all, it basically
means a little bit.
- A little bit, so you're just saying,
maybe you'll hear this
in maybe a cooking show,
or you'll read it in
books when they'll say,
a pinch of salt, or a touch
of salt, or a dash of salt.
- That's right, you could
even say it about other things.
For example, if my friend
just wrote this article,
and he wanted me to read it,
I say, "It's a really good article,
"but it could use
a touch of humor.
" And maybe if you made it a
little bit funny, it would be better.
- Or maybe if you're painting your house,
you can say, "Oh, I think a touch of red
paint "would look really nice on this wall.
" - That's right, a little bit
of red paint would be good.
- Okay, so a touch of a
really, really good phrase.
It makes you sound very natural.
Okay, so that's all the
time we have for today,
but before we go, let's
listen to the dialogue again.
(upbeat music)
- Welcome to our show.
Today, I'm going to show you how to
make the perfect mouth-watering sandwich.
Are you ready?
Let's get started.
Let's start with the basics, bread.
Bread is an important ingredient here.
You need to remember one thing.
Choose the bread
according to the following
criteria, freshness,
crumb, and color.
If you want a closed sandwich,
I recommend you first toast
your bread in a toaster or oven,
or grill it slightly until it
gets a light brown color.
Now that our bread is ready,
let's talk about the ingredients.
Of course, each person's palette is different,
but I'm going to give you a few tips
that you'll be able to use when turning
any sandwich into the perfect sandwich.
I would strongly recommend you
put fresh vegetables in your sandwich.
Do not undervalue them
as they play a big role
in forming the taste and will make
the sandwich more refreshing and light.
The best choices here are evident.
Cucumbers, tomatoes, onions, sweet pepper
or chili, lettuce, and of course, herbs.
You can't go wrong with them.
As for aubergines,
mushrooms, and asparagus,
I would recommend you first grill them
slightly with a little touch of olive oil.
Last but not least, we
have a wide variety of
condiments that we can
add to our perfect sandwich.
We can be subtle and add
just a touch of salt and pepper
or we can combine mustard
sauce, mayonnaise, ketchup,
or even caviar to
achieve a stronger flavor.
It's always a good idea to cut
your sandwich in triangles or
manageable pieces to avoid
all your ingredients falling out
and standing your shirt.
That's all the time we have for today,
but join us next time where we'll be
going over how to make the perfect lasagna.
So next time.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so talking about sandwich,
this really reminds me of making sandwiches
at home, grilled cheese sandwich.
We didn't really talk about it here,
but I think it's my favorite sandwich.
- The grilled cheese sandwich.
- Very easy to make, just two
pieces of bread and cheese inside.
- Do you use butter though?
- Yes.
- Yeah, so you have to butter the bread.
And so when you grill it, it
gets really nice and brown.
- Yeah, actually, I'm not
a very big sandwich fan
when I'm having, for
example, a meal like lunch.
I don't really, I don't
know, I think I need
something more solid
than just a sandwich at times.
- Interesting, I had a
sandwich for dinner last night.
- Yeah.
- That we speak about it, yeah.
I had an egg salad sandwich.
- Egg, so you had egg salad
inside two pieces of bread.
- That's right, but the
bread I had was French bread,
so that long thin bread was
very crunchy, very delicious.
But actually, I like sandwiches for dinner.
- There are a little bit lighter.
Yeah, when you're having a big meal,
it just seems like, although
maybe sometimes places
give you very big heavy
sandwiches that have, you know,
like ham and salami and just a lot of things
in there, so they're very, very filling.
- That's very true, like a meatball sub,
for example, is a very heavy sandwich.
- That's right.
- But sandwiches come
in all shapes and sizes.
You can make basically any
sandwich that your brain can think of.
And so we hope that you've learned some
words for talking about sandwiches today.
Of course, if you have
any questions or comments
or you wanna share
with us your very favorite
sandwich, you should
do so on EnglishPod.com.
- All right, we'll see you guys there.
- Bye, bye.
(upbeat music)